<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles of impeachment exhibited in Parliament, against Spencer Earle of Northamp William Earle of Devonsh. Henry Earle of Dover, Henry Earle of Monmouth, Robert Lord Rich, Charles Lord Howard Charlton, Charles L. Grey of Ruthen Thomas Lord Coventry, Arthur Lord Chapell, &amp;c. For severall high crimes and misdemeanors. Whereunto is annexed, the grounds of the proceedings of the Parliament from the beginning to this present, with the hinderances of their proceedings and causes of these distractions. Together with the severall meanes which they have used to prevent intestine warre, and to hinder the malignant designes of the enemies of the peace of the kingdome. Likewise ordered to be printed. Jo. Browne Cler. Parl.</title>
            <author>Northampton, Spencer Compton, Earl of, 1601-1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82546</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1234</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E153_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20771</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866746</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866746</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119031</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82546)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119031)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 27:E153[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles of impeachment exhibited in Parliament, against Spencer Earle of Northamp William Earle of Devonsh. Henry Earle of Dover, Henry Earle of Monmouth, Robert Lord Rich, Charles Lord Howard Charlton, Charles L. Grey of Ruthen Thomas Lord Coventry, Arthur Lord Chapell, &amp;c. For severall high crimes and misdemeanors. Whereunto is annexed, the grounds of the proceedings of the Parliament from the beginning to this present, with the hinderances of their proceedings and causes of these distractions. Together with the severall meanes which they have used to prevent intestine warre, and to hinder the malignant designes of the enemies of the peace of the kingdome. Likewise ordered to be printed. Jo. Browne Cler. Parl.</title>
                  <author>Northampton, Spencer Compton, Earl of, 1601-1643.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>July, 1. London, Printed by T.F. for J.Y.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Berkshire, Charles Howard, --  Earl of, ca. 1615-1679 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Coventry, Thomas Coventry, --  Baron, 1606-1661 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Devonshire, William Cavendish, --  Earl of, 1617-1684 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dover, Henry Carey, --  Earl of, ca. 1580-1666 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Monmouth, Henry Carey, --  Earl of, 1596-1661 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Warwick, Robert Rich, --  Earl of, 1587-1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Capel of Hadham, Arthur Capel, --  Baron, 1610?-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Grey of Ruthin, Charles Longueville, --  Baron, 1618-1643 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Impeachments --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119031:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES of Impeachment exhibited in PARLIAMENT, AGAINST
<list>
                  <item>SPENCER Earle of <hi>Northamp</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>WILLIAM Eatle of <hi>Devonſh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>HENRY Earle of <hi>Dover</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>HENRY Earle of <hi>Manmouth,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>ROBERT Lord <hi>Rich,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>CHARLES Lord <hi>Howard Charlton,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>CHARLES L. <hi>Grey</hi> of <hi>Ruthen</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>THOMAS Lord <hi>Coventry,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>ARTHVR Lord <hi>Chapell, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For ſeverall high Crimes and Miſdemeanors</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Ordered to be Printed.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Hen. Elſing Cler. D. C</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed, The Grounds of the Proceedings of the Parliament from the beginning to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, with the hinderances of their Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and cauſes of theſe diſtractions</p>
            <p>TOGETHER With the ſeverall meanes which they have uſed to prevent inteſtine Warre, and to hinder the malignant Deſignes of the enemies of the Peace of the Kingdome</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Likewiſe ordered to be Printed</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Jo. Browne Cler. Parl.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>July, 1. LONDON, Printed by <hi>T. F.</hi> for <hi>J. Y.</hi> 1642</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:119031:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119031:2"/>
            <head>Articles of Impeachment againſt the Nine Lords.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Aſſembled in Parliament, finding the diſtractions of the Kingdome to be great, have thought ſit to explaine, and remonſtrate to the world the grounds of their proceedings, and the cauſes of theſe diſtractions, in theſe enſuing particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Roote of theſe miſchievous deſignes</item>
               <item>2. The maturity to which they had attained fore the beginning of this Parliament</item>
               <item>3. The effectuall meanes which hath beene uſed for the extirpation of thoſe deſperate evils
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119031:3"/>
and the progreſſion which therein has beene made by the wiſdome of the Parliament.</item>
               <item>4. The wayes of oppoſition, by which that progreſſe is interrupted.</item>
               <item>5. The courſes to be taken for the removing of theſe obſtacles, and for the accompliſhing of our faithfull endeavours of reſtoring the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Honour, greatneſſe, and ſecurity of this Crowne and Nation, the roote of all this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe we find to be a malignant deſigne of ſubverting the fundamentall Lawes, upon which the Religion and Juſtice of this Kingdome are firmely eſtabliſhed.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Actors hereof have beene,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The Papiſts, which hate the Lawes, as the obſtacles of that ſubverſion of Religion, which they ſo much long for.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Such Councellors, and Courtiers, as for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ends, have ingaged themſelves to further the intereſts of Forraigne Princes, or States, to the prejudice of his Majeſty, and the State at home.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The common Principles by which they governe their Actions, are theſe.
<list>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119031:3"/>
                  <item>1. <hi>To maintaine continuall Differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the King and the People, upon queſtions of Prerogative, and Liberty, that ſo they may gaine to themſelves, and their parties, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt places of truſt and power in the Kingdome.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>To ſuppreſſe the purity of Religion, and ſuch perſons as were beſt affected to it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>To diſaffect the King to Parliaments, by ſlanders, and falſe imputations, and by putting him upon other wayes of ſupply, which in ſhow were fuller of advantage, then the ordinary courſe of Subſidies, which indeed have been the greateſt cauſe of theſe troubles and diſtractions under which we ſuffer.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Heere are the Authors, and cauſes of theſe diſtempers made manifeſt, now it is neceſſary to declare how farre theſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs have extended.</p>
            <p>Former relations, and precedent Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations have made ſome apparent, but yet ſo great is the power of ambition, that the infliction and execution of the Law upon <hi>Strafford,</hi> the durance and impriſonment of divers others of that faction, can no
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119031:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
way deterre them from uſing all meanes to perfect their deſignes, and finding no way ſo apt for their purpoſes, as to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment lealoufies betwixt the King and Parliament, they have caſt many odionse ſcandals upon the proceedings of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nay ſo farre has their treachery ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonded, that they have ſeduced divers Members of the Parliament, (namely) <hi>Spencer</hi> Earle of <hi>Northanmpton, William</hi> Earle of <hi>Devonſhire, Henry</hi> Earle of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth, Charles</hi> Lord <hi>Howard</hi> of <hi>Charlton, Robert</hi> Lord <hi>Rich, Charles</hi> Lord <hi>Grey</hi> of <hi>Ruthen, Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Coventry,</hi> and <hi>Arthur</hi> Lord <hi>Chapell,</hi> who are Impeacht for theſe high crimes and heinous miſdemeanors, following.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That contrary to their dutie, they being Peeres of the Realme, and ſummoned by writ to attend the Parliament, and contrary to an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Houſe of Peeres, of the ninth of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill <hi>laſt, and ſeverall other Orders, requiring the attendance of the ſaid Houſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119031:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
2. <hi>That after a Vote paſſed in both Houſes the 20. of</hi> May <hi>laſt, that the King ſeduced by wicked Councell intends to make Warre againſt his <hi>Parliament, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
It was Voted that the departure of theſe nine Lords without leave at ſuch a time, when the Houſe had declared that the King intended to make Warre againſt his Parliament, and their ſtill continuing at <hi>Yorke,</hi> notwithſtanding their ſummons, and command, is a high affront, and contempt of both Houſes, and that the ſaid Lords did as much as in them lav, that the buſineſſe of Parliament might be deſerted, and are iuſtly ſuſpected to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote a Warre againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p>For that they have by another Order of the 30, of <hi>May,</hi> beene duly ſummoned, by the Houſe of Peeres, to make their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance before that Houſe, upon the 8. day of <hi>June</hi> laſt paſt, they refuſed to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, and returned a ſcornefull Anſwer, by a Letter under their Hand, directed to the <hi>Speaker</hi> of the Lords Houſe, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119031:5"/>
remaining there upon Record.</p>
            <p>For which Crimes, and miſdemeanor (they tending to the diſſolution of the Parliament) and diſturbance of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. It is demanded by the Commons that the ſaid Lords may be brought to their Anſwer, and receive ſpeedy andex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary puniſhment, according to their demerits.</p>
            <closer/>
            <postscript>
               <p>Ordered by the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, that this both printed and publiſhed.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Hen. Elſing, Cler. C. D.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
